<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Joyful news for all Christendom. Being a happy prophesie of the Turks advancing to the Christian borders, where they shall consult against all Europe, and divide their whole power into three potent armies; one shall march into Poland and Silecia, the other towards the Rhine into France, and the third through the middle of Austria. With the gallant deportment of the Christians against their mighty armies, and the manner how they shall be utterly destroyed in 1662. Being a true copy taken out of the original March 16. 1661.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87395</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867122</idno>
  <idno type="VID">169370</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240922016</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1131</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1086_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208135</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867122</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99867122e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87395)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169370)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 161:E1086[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Joyful news for all Christendom. Being a happy prophesie of the Turks advancing to the Christian borders, where they shall consult against all Europe, and divide their whole power into three potent armies; one shall march into Poland and Silecia, the other towards the Rhine into France, and the third through the middle of Austria. With the gallant deportment of the Christians against their mighty armies, and the manner how they shall be utterly destroyed in 1662. Being a true copy taken out of the original March 16. 1661.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Jones,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 2d".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Europe --  History --  Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Turkey --  History --  Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169370:1"/>
            <p>JOYFUL NEWS FOR ALL Christendom.</p>
            <p>BEING A HAPPY PROPHESIE OF THE Turks advancing to the Christian Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, where they shall Consult against all <hi>Europe,</hi> and divide their whole Power into three Potent Armies; One shall march into <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Silecia,</hi> the other towards the <hi>Rhine</hi> into <hi>France,</hi> and the third through the middle of <hi>Austria.</hi> With the gallant deportment of the <hi>Christians</hi> against their mighty Armies, and the manner how they shall be utterly destroyed in 1662.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Being a true Copy taken out of the Original▪</hi> March 16. 1661.</p>
            <p>
               <add>Aprill 2<seg rend="sup">d</seg>
               </add> LONDON, Printed for <hi>J. Jones,</hi> 1661.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:169370:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169370:2"/>
            <head>A STRANGE PROPHESIE OF The utter destruction of the Turks upon their entring the Borders of Christendome, in the year 1662.</head>
            <p>SEveral Prophesies have been put forth to publick view Predicting the many and various Changes, which in late times should happen in divers Kingdoms, and Empires, some of which have been already in part fulfilled, to the exceeding great depopulation of some Princes Dominions; yet when ruined Kingdoms have been well mended from Head to Foot, proportions duly admeasured,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169370:3"/> and Justice justly dispenced to all, then have Rulers and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects sat down under their own Vines, and enjoyed the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of their own labours in peace; but till then the gayest Kingdoms shall be ruffling, scuffling, removing and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Hovells.</p>
            <p>For <hi>England,</hi> though the upper Stories have been shroad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly shaken and shattered of late years, by the tumultuous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion of a Schismattical generation of Seditious Phanaticks, yet the frame thereof being good, or mendable by the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Architectors now at work, there is good hopes that a happy and perfect peace, will be soon settled throughout the Dominions of his Royal Majesty.</p>
            <p>I doubt not but that our Master Builders will remember, that punctuallity in Divinity and Policy, is but regularity. Ecclesiastical Reformation is that God expects, He stands not upon new invented Synods, but upon his own Terms; and will have all his Vessels &amp; Ordinances cast in his own mould, as formerly they were.</p>
            <p>He that stands not for the Crown, minds not the preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his Body, nor the good of his own Soul; for the life of a Subject consists in the safety of his Prince, and the prosperity of his Royal Council; therefore we may well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce that the work is fallen into the hands and Hearts of such noble Senators, who will weigh <hi>Rules</hi> with <hi>Troy</hi> weight. But not to insist further by way of preamble, I shall not make mention of the Prophesies of <hi>Merlin, Shiptons</hi> Wife, or that learned Cardinal, <hi>David</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> the last of which is fulfilled in the happy Restoration of our Royal Sovereigne King <hi>Charles the Second;</hi> I shall only here insert a saying of the Great <hi>Turk,</hi> and so come to the Prophecy here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, When several Musicians were long a tuneing their Instruments, he hearing them said, <hi>I think it not to stand with my State, to wait for what will follow.</hi> But all Christians that hear the happy tydings or Musick of this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Prophesie, (though delivered by a Heathen) may well waite with patience for the expiration of this so happy
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169370:3"/> prediction, from whence so great benefit shall redound to all <hi>Europe;</hi> For the fulfilling of which, I question not but all Christian Princes will provide in time, for repulsing so dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, blasphemous and potent an enemy as these barbarous and inhumane Infidels.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The true Copy of the Prophesie.</head>
               <p>ABout the space of four years and a half age, a Seaman making a Voyage from <hi>Lubeck,</hi> in a Merchants Ship that was bound for the <hi>Straits,</hi> in the way was unhappily set upon by some barbarous <hi>Turkish</hi> Pyrats, by whom after a short dispute he was taken Prisoner amongst other Marriners that was in the said Ship, who were all sold like sheep in the Market. But above all the rest the aforesaid Seamen, was sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled forth, and carried about five hundred miles, and sold to a learned <hi>Turk,</hi> who after a small time of his continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with him, looked upon his slave with great diligence, and taking notice of his countenance, began to speak with him in the <hi>Saxon</hi> Tongue after this manner.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>First, He asked him, Whether he came not from <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly, Whether his and his Wives name were not such and such?</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, Whether his dwelling was not in such and such a place?</item>
                  <item>Fourthly, Whether he did not come in such a ship, and so was taken prisoner.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The said Seaman hearing all that had been said, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the truth thereof, being greatly amazed, did certainly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he was some great Prophet.</p>
               <p>Again, the <hi>Turk</hi> asked his slave, whether he would shew mercy to him one time for another, and if he should give him his liberty, which he should promise him by his God and his Christ whom he served? The slave did it with great willingness.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:169370:4"/>
               <p> The <hi>Turk</hi> said further unto him, First of all I command thee to go to <hi>Lubeck</hi> (the place of thy former abode) to which end and purpose I will give thee sufficient means, and also assist thee in thy journey, that thou mayst thereby safely arrive at the Christian Borders.</p>
               <p>And when thou comest thither thou shalt find in such a place (the which he gave him a particular token of) in thy own yard a Pot buried, wherein is a large sum of money, out of that mony, take one thousand five hundred pounds <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck,</hi> and give them to thy Wife for the subsistance of her, thy Children, and the rest of thy Family; but the rest be sure thou bring hither unto me for thy Ransome, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards I shall freely declare unto thee my desire.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Turke</hi> having finisht his Speech, the Seaman, who was his Slave (being accommodated with all necessary for so tedious a journey, according to the promise of this Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Turk)</hi> betook himself to his journey, and coming to the place appointed found all things according to the <hi>Turks</hi> saying, the which he neglected not, but with all diligence performed every thing faithfully &amp; punctally as he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</p>
               <p>But after the space of twenty Moneths, he returned from <hi>Lubeck</hi> and safely came to his Patron; to whom he deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the remainder of the money.</p>
               <p>As soon as the <hi>Turk</hi> had rrceived the money of the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, he counted it over, and finding it right (according to his expectation) he spake unto his Slave saying, I perceive now that thou art the man whom I have sought and desired this long time, and that thou fearest thy God, seeing thou hast taken nothing of that money but what I commanded thee and hast brought me the rest without deceipt, Now therefore I will declare unto thee my desire.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:169370:4"/>
               <p> Behold, About four years hence our <hi>Turkish</hi> States shall gather together and come to the Christian Borders, and being Assembled, they shall consult together, whether they shall drink of the Christians blood, or whether the Christians shall drink of their blood?</p>
               <p>The result whereof will be this, That they shall divide their whole Power into three parts; The one whereof shall march to the right, into <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Silecia,</hi> the other to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Rhine</hi> into <hi>France,</hi> and the third through the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of <hi>Austria;</hi> and so shall come up to <hi>Lubeck,</hi> where I shall be also.</p>
               <p>Behold, we shall there be repulsed by the Christians, and after a sharpe dispute, we shall be overthrown and utterly destroyed; and I shall lye dead in such a place (the which he named unto this Seaman) in a peculiar habit, and the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of those that shall be slain, shall be very great; and this Battel shall be called, <hi>The Battel upon the Mountain of Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I intreat thee to shew me this mercy, to bury me in my Mothers Bosome, and so to incorporate me; therefore go thy waies, and wait for that time: And behold, all this money which thou hast brought for thy Ransome, I give it to thee again, wherewith thou mayst thy self, thy Wife and Children with the rest of thy Family susteine in Peace and quietnesse.</p>
               <p>Now three years and a half are almost expired, since the aforesaid Seaman departed from the <hi>Turk</hi> who made known this Prophesie to him, And he dwells now in <hi>Lubeck,</hi> where he diligently waits for the time, that he may perform his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise to his Patron.</p>
               <p>Thus may we discover out of this forgoing Prediction, that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169370:5"/> the destruction of that cursed <hi>Magog,</hi> the <hi>Turkish Empire,</hi> who hath been a continual scourge to all <hi>Europe,</hi> is near at hand: So that there is great hopes of a happy unanimity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween all Princes in <hi>Christendom,</hi> by which means <hi>England</hi> as well as other Nations will enjoy true Peace and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness under a gracious Soveraign, whom God preserve from the conspiracy of all factious Phanatick Spirits for ever.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>